AMIT KUMAR

Address: Sammakorn Condominium, Sammakorn Soi 18 Ramkhamhaeng 112,

Bangkok 10240, Thailand

Mobile: (+66) 0925035043, (+91) 9953571101

E-mail: amit.kr.py@gmail.com

Data Scientist/Engineer with over 12 years of experience in credit risk, healthcare and retail industries with organizations and teams from several geographies and diverse backgrounds. Adaptive personality, being a mix of team player, mentor or leader as a project demands. Mathematics major with a knack for problem solving. Expertise in Machine Learning with sound theoretical understanding of algorithms and application of Statistical methods to business problems. Consistently brought value to products, clients and teams with a high ROI on projects of diverse nature. Currently looking for an opportunity for a long-term role.

Values: Integrity, inclusiveness, professionalism, mutual respect, collaboration, learning and growth

EDUCATION

MSc and BSc in Mathematics and Computing

Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur, India

2006-2011

SKILLS

- Python, R, SAS, SQL, NoSQL, Tableau, AWS, GCP, Cloudera
- Machine Learning, Statistics, Forecasting, Regression, Clustering, Network Analysis, Business Intelligence, A/B Testing, Dashboards
- LLMs, FastAI, OpenAI API, GPT-4, BART, langchain, llama-2, hugging face
- Tensorflow, PyTorch, Pandas, scikit-learn, NumPy, SciPy, Matplotlib, seaborn, iGraph, Streamlit
- Kubernetes, Redis, Django, Celery
- GitHub, GitLab, CD/Cl, Agile, Scrum
- React.js, Javascript, npm

EXPERIENCE

MAQE Aug 2022 to Present
Bangkok, Thailand

Job title: Lead Data Scientist/AI ML

- Developed an LLM based Text-to-SQL generative model and implemented a chatbot to interact with a database and provide game statistics to users for a sport website
- Developed an Image Recognition API to detect products for a client app with 98% accuracy
- Worked on a long-term engagement with a Europe based financial client company to help with developing and maintaining machine learning models and automating internal business processes to enable faster decision making
- Developed several POC applications end to end from collecting data, developing models and interactive interfaces for demo

Agoda Jul 2020 to Apr 2022
Bangkok, Thailand

Job title: Senior Analyst

- Proactively delivered insights and recommendations on productivity, organizational changes, recruitment and talent
- Automated organizational manual processes extensively with Python and real-time data flows
- Developed dashboards on key organizational metrics to facilitate decision making for senior leadership
- Coordinated and managed projects with stakeholders and leaders across multiple teams in the organization

Contract Consulting Jan 2018 to Apr 2019 Gurgaon, India

AI/ML Developer (Consultant)

Developed an automated forecasting API service for time-series data using Django and Celery frameworks in Python

- Won a project bid with a manufacturing giant by predicting their annual sales of products with 90% accuracy
- Led the development of dashboards with KPIs on credit risk underwriting and collections for app-based lending platform
- Innovated new approaches to detect fraud using Network Analysis and Graph Theory bringing down fraud rate by 25%
- Implemented a real-time visualization tool using Python iGraph for operations team to protect against fraudulent leads
- Built decision trees to underwrite users without a credit history that added 3% of new loans and 1% increase in revenue

McKinsey & Company Apr 2016 to May 2017 Gurgaon, India

Job title: Senior Analyst

- Devised a methodology to create savings through timely procurement of pharmacy and other medical supplies for a top hospital chain in the US that resulted in 3% savings on a spend base of \$10M over six months
- Built regression and time series models to predict prices of pharmacy supplies, with 80% accuracy in 5% error range
- Engaged with multiple major healthcare providers through analytics and machine learning on ad-hoc business problems
- Delivered scalable tools with R and Tableau to provide reporting solutions with plug-and-play type functionality on raw data

SCIO Health Analytics

Oct 2013 to Mar 2015 Hartford, USA and Chennai, India

Job title: Healthcare Data Analyst

- Developed regression models in SAS to identify 'impactable' medical conditions and quantify associated risk for a top health insurer in the US; 2% lift in accuracy over the client's existing models
- Innovated a joint probability based technique for transforming sparse medical claims data into significant predictors
- Built predictive models on utilization and pharmacy claims data for clinical and financial risk prediction, condition identification (to predict major surgeries) and fraud detection (payment integrity) for multiple clients

Global Analytics

Jun 2011 to Mar 2013

Chennai, India

Job title: Analyst

- Proposed new revenue segments to be opened up for a lending platform using predictive models built on R and Python
- Designed A/B tests and analyzed risk KPIs to manage portfolio of loans as part of risk monitoring team
- Conceptualized the underwriting structure for a newly launched consumer finance product

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Aalto University

Summers of 2009 and 2010

Helsinki, Finland

Job title: Research Assistant

• Worked as a student intern to assist the Head of Department, Mathematics and his research group on topics in numerical analysis